2025 has been an absolutely crazy year
for AI. So, right now, I'm taking on the
challenge to quickly cover for you
everything that has happened with AI
this year. And so, I'll be hitting on
the news that points to the trends going
into 2026 and who the big players will
be. And I can guarantee that I have
missed nothing on this list. Just
kidding, of course. I probably missed
something. So, definitely let me know in
the comments as I go through everything
what you think should be added to this
list. We have incredible new tools and
LLMs that have been released. AI coding
assistants are taking over the world.
Companies are raising billions of
dollars left and right with massive
acquisitions. A single tool is being
used by 90% of Fortune 500 companies
now. And of course, we have the Chinese
startup that wiped $600 billion off the
Nvidia market cap in a single day. So,
just a teaser for what we have here, but
I've got 50 items in the list. Let's go
ahead and dive right into it. So, I'm
going to start with the things that
apply to the entire year 2025. Then I'll
get into the specific events in
chronological order as they happened in
2025. And of course, I will link to all
these sources in the description. The
first baffling number out of many that
we have here is that companies have
invested $37 billion into enterprise AI
this year. That figure was only $1.7
billion in 2023. Also, 84% of developers
are using or planning on using AI tools
in their development process. And out of
all developers, about half are already
using AI coding assistants daily. In
2025, AI startups have captured almost
50% of all global funding. Just take a
look at how this has evolved from 2021.
It's absolutely insane. And speaking of
funding, this year 49 US AI startups
have raised at least $100 million.
And of course, we have the Chinese
startup that I alluded to earlier, the
release of Deep Seek R1. At the time, a
very revolutionary open-source large
language model. And this is highly
debated, but there are a lot of claims
that this is the reason the Nvidia
market cap went down $600 billion, the
largest one-day loss for a single
company in the US stock market history.
In January, we also had the announcement
of the Stargate project, a company
formed to invest $500 billion over the
next four years in building out new AI
infrastructure for OpenAI. And speaking
of OpenAI, soon after the Stargate
announcement, they also released
Operator, the agent that uses its own
browser to perform millions of different
tasks for you. Now, whether or not this
lived up to the hype, I'll leave that up
to you to decide, but it was a big deal
at the start of this year. Going into
February now, the AI engineer Andrej
Karpathy coined the term vibe coding,
and it has gained so much popularity
that it literally has its own Wikipedia
page now. It's official. Now, AI
regulation in general is a bit too in
the weeds for me to cover here, but
there is one instance that deserves a
spot on the list, is the EU AI Act, the
first-ever comprehensive legal framework
on AI worldwide. And we're definitely
going to see a lot more regulation like
this going into 2026. And now for the
first of many funding rounds and
valuations that I'll cover in this
video, we have Harvey, the legal AI
startup raising $300 million in their
Series D. A lot of people don't realize
this, but the legal industry is a
goldmine of opportunity for generative
AI. Now, March was a very big month for
generative AI, especially because that's
when Anthropic's model context protocol
really took off. But that doesn't belong
in this list because it was originally
created at the very end of 2024. So, for
the first March item, we have Manis, the
first of its kind general AI agent that
really was the pioneer for a lot of
strategies around context engineering
that we have now and strategies for
building agents that can handle more
long-running tasks. Google also released
Gemma 3, their next open-source large
language models built on the same
technology and research that powered
their Gemini 2.0 models. And speaking of
Gemini, Google released Gemini 2.5 later
this month as well. And this model was
revolutionary because of how well it
handled a large amount of context. And
it stood the test of time for quite a
while, generally considered to be the
best general-purpose large language
model for many months. And as 2025
progressed, there were so many insane
valuations and acquisitions and funding
rounds. Starting now with the very end
of March, OpenAI raised $40 billion,
which put them at a $300 billion
post-money valuation. Now, going into
the month of April, Meta released their
Llama 4 models. They have their herd
here, three different options that we
have, Behemoth, Maverick, and Scout.
Now, we haven't actually seen much from
Meta since then. And so, I really hope
that going into 2026, we'll get maybe
Llama 5. I really hope that Meta picks
up the slack here. Then we have OpenAI
releasing their O3 and O4 mini models,
continuing to push the limits for what
is possible with the reasoning
capabilities built into these LLMs that
is so common now. And then going back to
open-source, Alibaba released their Qwen
3 models at the very end of April. And
these are still some of my favorite
open-source large language models to
use. They really have stood the test of
time. Now, going into May, OpenAI
introduced Codex, their cloud-based
software engineering agent that
integrates directly with GitHub, so you
can work on your repos remotely. even
have to be in your local development
environment. They also released the
Codex CLI later. This still is one of my
favorite platforms for AI-assisted
coding. We also had the release of VEO3
from Google. This is when AI video
generation started to finally actually
feel good. OpenAI agrees to buy Windsurf
for $3 billion, only for the deal to
fall apart a couple months later in July
with Windsurf CEO going to Google. It
pretty much seems like Google acquired
Windsurf, especially with all the
features that come out in antigravity,
Google's new agentic IDE that was
released along with Gemini 3 that we'll
talk about later. Anthropic released
their family of Claude 4 models. This is
when Claude really became the coding
king for me, and I got obsessed with
using Claude code. It still, in my mind,
is the best agentic coding assistant.
Now, going into June, Cursor reached
$500 million in annually recurring
revenue. At this point, it was very
clear that Cursor was the
fastest-growing platform and still is in
SaaS history. Also this month, Mark
Zuckerberg announced the creation of the
Meta Superintelligence Labs. This is
when we had all the drama of Mark
Zuckerberg apparently paying all of
these nine-figure salaries to poach top
researchers from other companies. Now,
going into July, Amazon has released
their own coding agent Hero, which is an
AI coding assistant that I'm starting to
respect more and more. And I heard that
after their re:Invent conference in
December, they are starting to get a lot
of enterprise interest. And at the end
of July, open-source large language
models continue to fight back. Moonshot
released to Kimmy K2, which apparently,
according to the benchmarks, beat
ChatGPT and Claude in coding. This is
very much up for debate, but I still do
like seeing open-source LLMs pushing the
boundaries. All right, so we have been
blitzing through a lot already. So,
let's take a quick break for our
sponsor, and then we'll get back to
finishing off our list. So, the sponsor
of this video is Zapier, which is
actually my original no-code automation
tool. They've built a lot in the AI
space this year, including the Zapier
MCP server, which allows you to connect
your agent to over 8,000 different
applications. So, literally, no matter
the capabilities that you want to build
into your agent, you can do it with the
Zapier MCP. Take a look at how easy this
is. First, all you have to do is set up
the app connections in Zapier. So, you
go through the OAuth flow or whatever to
get your credentials, like for Google
Drive, connected. And then you go into
the MCP server tab, which I'll link to
in the description, to set up your
server. You pick your client, and then
you pick your tools. search through all
of the services that are available, like
I can do Google Drive, for example. You
pick the individual tools that you want
in the MCP, and you configure all of the
parameters. Once you have that set up,
then you go to the connect tab. And
right here, there's a button to just add
it directly into Claude desktop. Or for
other MCP clients, you can just copy
this URL and set it up just like you
would a typical streamable HTTP MCP
server. And so, for example, in Claude
desktop, I'll go to the settings in the
top right, and then I will go to the
connectors, I can add a custom
connector, and I just have to paste in
the URL that I copied here, and I can
call it Zapier, and then boom, you are
good to go. It'll take you through an
OAuth flow with Zapier so that it's nice
and secure, but then you will
immediately have it available as
capabilities to Claude desktop. And so,
for a very quick demonstration, I used
the Zapier MCP server in Claude desktop
to find my Google Drive folder and
create a file here. So, you can see both
tool calls, everything's working
perfectly, and we even have the file at
the bottom here, so I can click right
into it in my Google Drive. And it was
so easy to set this all up. And so, I
will have a link in the description to
the Zapier MCP server. Definitely check
it out. Now, surprisingly, August was a
pretty quiet month for generative AI.
The biggest thing that we had was the
introduction of GPT-5 from OpenAI.
Getting into September now, we have more
funding. The funding train that never
stops. Anthropic raises $13 billion,
putting it now at a $183 billion
valuation. Now, there have been a lot of
lawsuits in the AI space this year, but
one of the interesting ones that
happened more recently is a group of
authors sued Anthropic for using their
books and other materials in their
training data. And Anthropic ended up
paying a whopping $1.5 billion
settlement. Now, I don't mean to just
pick on Anthropic here. There are a lot
of different lawsuits for all of the LLM
providers, but it is crazy. They're
paying around $3,000 for each of the
estimated 500,000 books covered by the
settlement. Also in September,
Perplexity, the AI search startup,
raises $200 million at a $20 billion
valuation. Very impressive to me that
Perplexity has stayed on the cutting
edge and remained competitive even
though people think time and time again
that all of the common agents and LLMs
are going to replace Perplexity with
their built-in search. And continuing
the funding train, Mistral, the French
AI startup, raised 1.7 billion euros.
continue to put out some of my favorite
open-source LLMs and a lot of their
closed-source stuff is really powerful
as well. And finally, to end things off
in September, OpenAI released Sora 2.
And this, my friend, took the world by
storm. The capabilities here for both
the video and audio generation is just
insanely cool. And continuing with
OpenAI going into October, Sam Altman
said that in October, ChatGPT hit 800
million weekly active users. I wish my
applications had that many weekly active
users. Also, IBM and Anthropic announced
a partnership to accelerate the
development of enterprise-ready AI. I
was actually there at the IBM Tech
Exchange conference when they announced
this. Very, very cool. Anthropic is
definitely continuing to push themselves
as the enterprise LLM provider,
especially for coding. Now getting into
November, Microsoft announced the
formation of the MAI superintelligence
team. What they're working towards here
is humanist superintelligence.
Incredibly advanced AI capabilities that
always work for and service of people
and humanity more generally. Now this is
kind of vague to me right now, but I
think we're going to find out a lot more
about this going into 2026. Anthropic
releases Claude code for the web.
Certainly a competitor to OpenAI's Codex
that I talked about earlier. Being able
to work on your repositories with agents
running remotely, so you're not even in
your local development environment. I
definitely think this is the future of
agentic coding. Something I'm even
working on myself, building custom
systems for remote agentic coding. Then
Google takes AI image generation to the
next level with Nano Banana, especially
Nano Banana Pro, which was released at
the end of November. It is insane the
quality of images that we can generate
with AI and especially how realistic
they look now. Microsoft, Nvidia, and
Anthropic all announced partnerships. So
Anthropic to scale Claude on Azure,
Anthropic to adopt Nvidia architecture,
and Nvidia and Microsoft to invest in
Anthropic. So definitely a bit of a
circular investment here, which speaks a
little bit to the possibility of an AI
bubble, but it makes sense for all these
big companies to be working together.
And we right now are only halfway
through November. There's so much that
happened last month. Next, we have the
release of Gemini 3 from Google, which
is often considered to be the most
powerful LLM from a general standpoint
right now. It absolutely crushes it on
the benchmarks and handles long context
tasks very well. Now at the start of
this video, I alluded to the fact that
there is a single application that is
already adopted by over 90% of Fortune
500 companies. And that application is
Microsoft 365 Copilot. And I believe
they reached that 90% mark in November
of last year. It's just absolutely crazy
the enterprise adoption for a single
product. Anthropic continues to crush it
with Claude code. Claude code reaches $1
billion in revenue. And Anthropic
acquires Bun, the JavaScript runtime, to
continue to make Claude code more and
more scalable. Because let me tell you,
the demand for it is incredible. On top
of that, Anthropic releases Claude Opus
4.5, which most people will tell you
that it's not even a competition. It is
the AI coding king. Sonnet 4.5 was
already amazing, but now Opus is just
crushing it for AI coding. Now there
hasn't been that much news around
DeepSeek since the start of the year.
But now going into December, they
released DeepSeek version 3.2, an
open-source large language model that
competes with all of the big guys,
Gemini, Claude, and GPT. Now this is
open-source, but it's such a large model
that most people can't actually run it
on their own hardware, which is a bit of
a bummer. But unfortunately, that is
what it takes right now to compete with
all of the top dogs. And continuing with
open-source LLMs, we also have the
release of GLM 4.7, an LLM that is
designed specifically to be very
powerful for AI-assisted coding. And in
the benchmarks, it compares extremely
well to the DeepSeek version 3.2 we just
covered, Claude Sonnet 4.5, GPT 5.1. The
point of these open-source models is
that they're almost as powerful as the
big guys, but they are a lot faster and
cheaper. So Anthropic's model context
protocol really took off earlier this
year. And now in December, they
announced that they're donating MCP as a
part of establishing the agentic AI
foundation. This is a directed fund
under the Linux Foundation, co-founded
by Anthropic, Block, and OpenAI with
support from a lot of other absolutely
massive companies. And so hopefully what
this means is that all these companies
are starting to work together to build
out AI for the greater good. Now as much
as MCP is incredible, Anthropic also
recently released Claude skills. They
did this back in October. It's really
started to gain traction this month in
December though. And it's becoming a
replacement in a lot of ways for MCP cuz
it's a lot more context optimized. And
so it's this idea of progressive
disclosure where we only give
capabilities to our agents when it
actually needs them. So we save a lot of
context up front. This kind of paradigm
is going to be very popular going into
2026 for building any kind of agentic
system. Definitely not limited to the
Claude ecosystem either. OpenAI releases
GPT 5.2. Definitely a lot of
improvements over GPT 5.1. Now Anthropic
with Claude seems to be quite focused on
AI coding as the specialization of the
LLMs. But GPT is more general-purpose
like Gemini, so seems to be kind of
competing more with Gemini 3. OpenAI
also gets a $1 billion investment from
Disney, especially thanks to Sora.
Definitely showing that there is a lot
of use case and demand for AI-generated
videos with audio. So we haven't talked
about data companies that much in this
video, but they're certainly doing well,
too. Databricks is doing their over $4
billion series L and is valued now at
$134
billion. They also acquired Neon
recently, one of my favorite database
platforms. They're definitely rocking
it. And then at the very end of this
year, Nvidia announced that they are
buying Groq's assets for about $20
billion.
Now the title is kind of strange cuz it
doesn't say it's an acquisition, but it
definitely feels like an acquisition
when you really dive into it. So
definitely a lot of interesting things
that will unfold here going into January
as well. All right, to end things off
for us here, I literally have an article
dated December 30th of this year. Meta
is going to acquire Manifold. And it's
cool cuz I talked about both of these
companies already. Manifold was very
revolutionary when it was released at
the start of this year. And Meta hasn't
made a splash in the generative AI space
in a while now. And so it definitely
seems like they're doing some things
behind the scenes that we might find out
about more, maybe quarter one or quarter
two of next year. And so they're going
to be integrating Manifold into its
products, including Meta AI. All right,
so that, my friend, is all the big
things that happened in the AI space in
2025. So definitely let me know in the
comments if you think there's anything
that I missed. And also what you're
looking forward to going into 2026. And
in January, I'll definitely be making
some content on my predictions and what
I'm focusing on going into the new year.
So if you're looking forward to that or
just building AI agents and using coding
agents in general, I would really
appreciate a like and a subscribe. And
with that, I will see you in the next
video.